Guide to the John Ricci Papers MC 156
New York University Archives
John Ricci Papers
1920-1980
MC 156
New York University Archives
0.5 linear feet
This collection contains photographs, memorabilia, and correspondence relating to John Ricci's tenure as a professor of chemistry at New York University.
Arrangement
The collection consists of two series, in which items are arranged chronologically. Series I consists of photos, memorabilia and correspondence related to Ricci's student days and teaching career at the University. Series II consists of photos and related correspondence given to Ricci from students on his retirement.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Biography of John Ricci
John E. Ricci (1907-1999) taught chemistry in New York University's College of Arts and Science from 1931 until his retirement as professor in 1973. He received bachelor's, master's, and doctoral degrees in chemistry from NYU and chaired the University College Committee on Recommendations to the Medical and Dental Schools. In 1960 he received one of three Great Teacher Awards from the University's Alumni Federation.
Ricci was a member of several honorary societies, including Phi Beta Kappa and the American Chemical Society, where he was associate editor of the Society's journal. He was also a consultant to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission through the Los Alamos and Oak Ridge National Laboratories.
He wrote more than 70 research articles, most in the Journal of the American Chemical Society. He also authored two books: The Phase Rule and Heterogeneous Equilibrium and Hydrogen Ion Concentration, New Concepts in a Systematic Treatment.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of photographs taken during and honoring Ricci's teaching career at New York University. Most are of Department of Chemistry faculty and students. Included are some photos of the University Heights Campus. The collection also contains items from Ricci's student days at NYU during the 1920s and correspondence related to Ricci's appointment to several New York City councils and academic honorary societies.
American Chemical Society.; Gwynne, Charles T.; Hill, Arthur E.; Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-; La Guardia, Fiorello H., (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Morris, Newbold; New York City Council of Defense.; New York University. Dept. of Chemistry.; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; Phi Beta Kappa. Alpha of New York (New York University).; Ricci, John E.; awards.; Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; New York University |x Special events.; New York University. University Heights Campus.; Photographs.
- Series I
  - Honorary Fraternity Keys of John Ricci, 1920-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1926 Commencement Program and NYU Class Day Program (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - NYU Class Day Program, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 1)
  - University Heights Chemistry Faculty 1924, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Department of Chemistry, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1)
    - Department of Chemistry, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 2)
    - Department of Chemistry, a., undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 3)
    - Department of Chemistry, b., undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 4)
  - Ricci with Prof. H. Austin Taylor and Prof. Milton Burton, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John E. Ricci, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
    - Nichols Hall, a., undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
    - Nichols Hall, b., undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 3)
  - 35 Year Service Award to Ricci, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Ricci Teaching Award to Arthur Tringali, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Second Ricci Teaching Award to Aidan Young, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ricci Symposium and Dinner, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ricci Correspondence, 1925-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II, 1973
  - Correspondence, notes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - University Heights Campus, Chemistry Lab, undated (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 1)
    - University Heights Campus, quadrangle, undated (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 2)
    - University Heights Campus, aerial view, undated (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 3)
    - Spring weekend, campus, undated (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 4)